Guide to the Jonathan Williams Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jonathan Williams photographs
1951-2007
1951-1997
YCAL MSS 757
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
32.1
(63 boxes)
The Jonathan Williams Photographs include portraits of persons in his social circle, principally poets, painters, writers, artists, and friends, as well as images of outsider art and artists, architecture, gravesites, and landscapes, circa 1951-circa 1997. The collection includes photograph albums of Polaroid prints, as well as loose Polaroid prints, color transparencies, black and white negatives, copy slides, and copy negatives. Overall, the images in the collection document Williams' work as a photographer, as well as his social network, interests, and activities. The collection also includes information about individual photographs provided by Williams and his partner, Thomas Meyer, 2006-2007.
Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008
Meyer, Thomas, 1947-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from James S. Jaffe on the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 2006-2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 63 (computer disk): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Existence and Location of Copies
Access to the database created by the processing archivist may be requested. Please consult with the appropriate curator.
Digital surrogates exist in the Beinecke Library's Digital Images Online database for most of the material in Series I and Series II.
Associated Materials
Jargon Society Collection, 1950-2008 (PCMS-0019). The Poetry Collection, State University of New York at Buffalo.
Jonathan Williams (1929-2008)
Jonathan Williams was a poet, publisher, and photographer. He was born Jonathan Chamberlain Williams in Asheville, North Carolina, the only child of Thomas Benjamin Williams (1898-1974) and Georgette Chamberlain Williams (1904-2000). Williams was educated at St. Albans School, Princeton University, and Black Mountain College, and studied art and design at the Institute of Design in Chicago.
Books of poetry by Williams include An Ear in Bartram's Tree (1969), Blues and Roots/Rue and Bluets (1971), The Loco Logodaedalus in Situ (1972), and Elite/Elate Poems (1979), while his books of photography include Portrait Photographs (1979) and A Palpable Elysium: Portraits of Genius and Solitude (2002).
In 1951, Williams founded the Jargon Society, a small-press publisher that publishes poetry, experimental fiction, photography, and folk art. As a poet and publisher, Williams was associated with the Black Mountain Poets. He also served as a contributing editor to the photography journal Aperture.
Williams and his partner of forty years, poet Thomas Meyer (born 1947), lived their summers at Corn Close, a seventeenth century shepherd's cottage in Dentdale in the Cumbrian hills of England and their winters at Skywinding Farm on Scaly Mountain, near Highlands, North Carolina.
Scope and Contents
The Jonathan Williams Photographs include portraits of persons in his social circle, principally poets, painters, writers, artists, and friends, as well as images of outsider art and artists, architecture, gravesites, and landscapes, circa 1951-circa 1997. The collection includes photograph albums of Polaroid prints, as well as loose Polaroid prints, color transparencies, black and white negatives, copy slides, and copy negatives. Overall, the images in the collection document Williams' work as a photographer, as well as his social network, interests, and activities. The collection also includes information about individual photographs provided by Williams and his partner, Thomas Meyer, 2006-2007.
Digital surrogates exist for significant portions of the collection and are available in the Beinecke Library's Digital Images Online database.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Photograph Albums, 1977-2007. II. Polaroid Prints, 1976-1994. III. Color Transparencies, circa 1951-circa 1997. IV. Black and White Negatives, circa 1951-circa 1988. V. Copy Photographs, circa 1978-circa 1993. VI. Electronic Files, 2006.
Architectural photography; Artists -- United States -- Portraits; Authors, American -- Portraits; Landscape photography; Outsider art -- United States -- Pictorial works; Poets, American -- Portraits; Portrait photography; Sepulchral monuments -- Pictorial works; Dentdale (England) -- Pictorial works; Great Britain -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white negatives; Born digital; Diffusion transfer prints; Photographic prints; Photograph albums; Slides (photographs); Transparencies; LGBTQ resource; Meyer, Thomas, 1947-; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008; Jargon Society
- Photographs Albums, 1977-2007; Series I; 7.3; (34 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged sequentially by the numbers Williams applied to individual albums, followed by image identifications that Williams and Meyer provided for the albums, and then a sample selection of the original albums without prints
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital surrogates exist in the Beinecke Library's Digital Images Online database for most of the material in Series I.
  General note
  For long-term preservation, the Polaroid prints were removed from their original "magnetic" photograph albums and rehoused in archival sheets and albums, which replicate their original arrangement and expression.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of photograph albums with more than 2700 Polaroid prints created and compiled in albums by Williams. The albums chiefly document his social circle and outsider art, as well as his travel throughout Europe and the United States.
  The Polaroid prints in these albums are a proprietary photographic format marketed by the Polaroid Corporation. The prints are made using a diffusion transfer process in film packets, which contains all of the developing chemicals and are exposed in a special camera.
  Identified individuals with significant quantities of informal portraits in the series include Donald B. Anderson, Basil Bunting, Mary Cooper, Simon Cutts, Sandra Fisher, Astrid Furnival, John Furnival, Ian Gardner, Mike Harding, Michael Heny, David Hockney, Robert Holmes, R. B. Kitaj, Todd Merrell, Anne Midgette, Stuart Mills, Raymond Moore, Karl Torok, and Erica Van Horn, as well as many portraits of Williams and Meyer.
  - Album No. 1, 1978-1987; 76 Polaroid prints (Box 1)
    This album documents a visit to the Black Forest in Germany, as well as Nancy, France, and Sissinghurst Castle in Kent, England
  - Album No. 2, circa 1980-circa 1985; 142 Polaroid prints (Box 2)
    This album documents a trip to the Dolomite Alps in Italy, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 3, 1987; 140 Polaroid prints (Box 3)
    This album documents a trip to a Black Mountain Conference at Bard College, New York, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 4, circa 1985; 65 Polaroid prints (Box 4)
    This album documents visits to English churches and sites in East Sussex, Gloucestershire, and Norfolk
  - Album No. 5, circa 1978-1986; 114 Polaroid prints (Box 5)
    This album documents sites along the Offa's Dyke Path National Trail along the border of Wales and England, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 6, circa 1988; 110 Polaroid prints (Box 6)
    This album documents a travel to the Black Forest in Germany and throughout England, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 7, circa 1990; 140 Polaroid prints (Box 7)
    This album documents sites along the Tour du Mont Blanc trail through parts of Switzerland, Italy and France, as well as a trip to Cardiff, Wales
  - Album No. 8, circa 1978-1982; 69 Polaroid prints (Box 8)
    This album documents persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale, as well as a visit to Rooksmoor House, the home of artists John Furnival and Astrid Furnival in Stroud, England
  - Album No. 9, circa 1992-1995; 81 Polaroid prints (Box 9)
    This album documents persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale, as well as a visit to Saltaire, England
  - Album No. 10, circa 1991; 106 Polaroid prints (Box 10)
    This album documents sites in the Pyrenees during a walking tour, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 11, 1987; 70 Polaroid prints (Box 11)
    This album documents artwork at Château de la Napoule in Mandelieu-la-Napoule, France, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 12, 1992-1993; 118 Polaroid prints (Box 12)
    This album documents sites in and around the At the Atlantic Center for the Arts in New Smyrna Beach, Florida, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 13, 1988-1989; 118 Polaroid prints (Box 13)
    This album documents artwork in the Collection de l'Art Brut in Lausanne, Switzerland, and sites in and around the Black Forest in Germany, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 14, circa 1981; 118 Polaroid prints (Box 14)
    This album documents persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 15, 1977-circa 1980; 71 Polaroid prints (Box 15)
  - Album No. 16, 1988; 80 Polaroid prints (Box 16)
    The album documents a trip by Williams and Mike Harding to Ireland. They published an account of the trip as Jonathan Williams and Mike Harding, Eight Days in Eire, or, Nothing so Urgent As Mañana (Rocky Mount, North Carolina: North Carolina Wesleyan College Press, 1990)
  - Album No. 17, circa 1978; 77 Polaroid prints (Box 17)
    This album documents churches and other sites throughout the United Kingdom, as well as Williams' visits with friends
  - Album No. 18, circa 1978; 74 Polaroid prints (Box 18)
  - Album No. 19, circa 1984; 75 Polaroid prints (Box 19)
    This album documents architectural details in Hexham Abbey in the town of Hexham, Northumberland, in northeast England, as well as persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale
  - Album No. 20, circa 1992; 73 Polaroid prints (Box 20)
    This album documents persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale, as well as architectural details Southwell Minster in Nottinghamshire, England
  - Album No. 21, circa 1983; 112 Polaroid prints (Box 21)
    This album documents persons visiting Williams' home in Dentdale, as well as sites along the Cotswold Way footpath in the Cotswolds of England
  - Album No. 22, circa 1984-1988; 62 Polaroid prints (Box 22)
    This album documents outsider art created by Ralph Griffin, James Harold Jennings, Thornton Dial, Sr., and others
  - Album No. 23, circa 1984-circa 1987; 116 Polaroid prints (Box 23)
    This album documents outsider art created by Vernon Lee Burwell, Carlos Cortez Coyle, Hermon Finney, Carl McKenzie, William Carlton Rice, and others
  - Album No. 24, circa 1984-circa 1988; 114 Polaroid prints (Box 24)
    This album documents outsider art created by Burlon Bart Craig, Howard Finster, Joe Louis Light, Eddie Owens Martin, Felix L. Virgous, and Enoch Tanner Wickham, and others, as well as a visit to Graceland in Memphis, Tennessee
  - Album No. 25, circa 1984; 114 Polaroid prints (Box 25)
    This album documents outsider art created by Raymond Coins, Dilmus Hall, Annie Hooper, James Harold Jennings, Clyde Jones, Mary Tillman Smith, Mose Ernest Tolliver, and others
  - Album No. 26, circa 1978-circa 1995; 171 Polaroid prints (Box 26)
    This album documents persons visiting Williams' homes in Dentdale and Scaly Mountain, as well as his visits to friends in Hartford, Connecticut, and London, England, and other places
  - Album No. 27, circa 1978-circa 1988; 115 Polaroid prints (Box 27)
    This album documents Williams' visits with friends in the United States and England
  - Album No. 28, circa 1978-circa 1986; 107 Polaroid prints (Box 28)
  - Image identifications provided by Jonathan Williams and Thomas Meyer, 2007 August; 28 (Box 29)
  - Empty album, undated (Box 30)
  - Empty album, undated (Box 31)
  - Empty album, undated (Box 32)
  - Empty album, undated (Box 33)
  - Empty album, undated (Box 34)
- Polaroid Prints, 1976-1994; Series II; 9.2; (10 boxes)
  Series II is arranged sequentially by numbers applied to each Polaroid print during processing.
  Digital surrogates exist in the Beinecke Library's Digital Images Online database for most of the material in Series II.
  This series consists of Polaroid prints created by Williams that document his social circle, travel, and interests.
  Identified individuals with significant quantities of portraits in the series include Michael Atkinson, Lyle Bongé, Shelley Brown, Simon Cutts, Sandra Fisher, Astrid Furnival, John Furnival, Mike Harding, Robert Holmes, R. B. Kitaj, Anne Midgette, Alvin Doyle Moore, as well as many portraits of Williams and Meyer.
  A group of images documents the exhibition "Jonathan Williams - A Poet Collects," which took place at the Southeastern Center for Contemporary Art in Winston-Salem, North Carolina, February 27-April 30, 1981.
  Identifications for individual images derive from item-level examination by the processing archivist compared to photograph albums in the collection.
  - T0001-T0250, 1976-1994 (Box 35)
  - T0251-T0500, 1976-1994 (Box 36)
  - T0501-T0800, 1976-1994 (Box 37)
  - T0801-T1050, 1976-1994 (Box 38)
  - T1051-T1320, 1976-1994 (Box 39)
  - T1321-T1621, 1976-1994 (Box 40)
  - T1622-T1910, 1976-1994 (Box 41)
  - T1911-T2192, 1976-1994 (Box 42)
  - T2193-T2476, 1976-1994 (Box 43)
  - T2477-T2693, 1976-1994 (Box 44)
- Color Transparencies, circa 1951-circa 1997; Series III; 14.3; (16 boxes)
  Series III is organized into seven subseries: Images Used in A Palpable Elysium, Portraits, Outsider Art, Architecture and Artwork, Gravesites, Landscapes, and Miscellaneous.
  This series consists of color transparencies on 120-millimeter film created by Williams and arranged by him into groups based on broad subjects.
  - Images Used in A Palpable Elysium
    Images compiled by for publication in Jonathan Williams, A Palpable Elysium: Portraits of Genius and Solitude (Boston, Massachusetts: David R. Godine, 2002).
    - PE0001-PE0080, circa 1955-circa 1995 (Box 45)
      PE66, Jack Spicer, Fort Bragg, California, was not received with the collection
  - Portraits
    This subseries consists of portraits of individuals, as well as views of birthplaces, homes, and gravesites related to persons admired by Williams.
    Identified individuals with significant quantities of portraits in this subseries include Lyle Bongé, Basil Bunting, Robert Creeley, Guy Davenport, Fielding Dawson, John Furnival, Jonathan Greene, Ronald Johnson, James Laughlin, Guy Mendes, Paul Metcalf, and Joel Oppenheimer, as well as many portraits of Williams and Meyer.
    - P0001-P0449, circa 1951-circa 1997 (Box 46)
    - P0450-P0999, circa 1951-circa 1997 (Box 47)
    - P1000-P1449, circa 1951-circa 1997 (Box 48)
    - P1450-P1950, circa 1951-circa 1997 (Box 49)
    - P1951-P2191, circa 1951-circa 1997 (Box 50)
  - Outsider Art
    This subseries includes images related to outsider art, including portraits of artists, as well as views of their environs and artwork.
    Individuals with significant representation in this subseries include James Butt, Ferdinand Cheval, Howard Finster, Raymond Isidore, Eddie Owens Martin, Clarence Schmidt, and Vollis Simpson.
    - OA001-OA538, circa 1955-circa 1995 (Box 51)
  - Architecture and Artwork
    This subseries includes images that depict mostly unidentified architecture and artwork, principally sculpture.
    The subseries has a significant quantity of images that depict Lanarkshire (later known as Little Sparta), a garden at Dunsyre in the Pentland Hills near Edinburgh, Scotland established by artist and poet Ian Hamilton Finlay (1925-2006) and his wife Sue Finlay in 1966.
    - A0001-A0420, circa 1968-circa 1986 (Box 52)
    - A0421-A0799, circa 1968-circa 1986 (Box 53)
    - A0800-A1230, circa 1968-circa 1986 (Box 54)
    - A1231-A1564, circa 1968-circa 1986 (Box 55)
  - Gravesites
    This subseries includes images of gravesites and monuments for persons admired by Williams.
    - G0001-G0250, undated (Box 56)
  - Landscapes
    This subseries includes images that depict mostly unidentified landscapes.
    The subseries has a significant quantity of images that depict the Callanish Stones near the village of Callanish on the west coast of Lewis in the Outer Hebrides, as well as views of Grand Canyon National Park and Bryce Canyon National Park in the United States.
    - L0001-L0300, undated (Box 57)
    - L0301-L0800, undated (Box 58)
    - L0801-L1010, undated (Box 59)
  - Miscellaneous
    This subseries includes images designated by Williams as miscellaneous. Significant quantities of images depict views of artwork, including works by Clyde Jones and Ian Hamilton Finlay, as well as buildings and landscapes.
    - M0001-M0455, circa 1961-circa 1984 (Box 60)
- Black and White Negatives, circa 1951-circa 1988; Series IV; 0.92; (1 box)
  Series IV is arranged sequentially by numbers applied to each negative by Williams.
  This series consists of black and white negatives that chiefly depict portraits, as well as views of landscapes and gravesites. The negatives are mostly single frames of 120-millimeter film, with a few examples of multiple frame negatives.
  Significant quantities of images in the series depict portraits of Basil Bunting, Jess Collins, Robert Creeley, Robert Duncan, Ronald Johnson, Christopher Middleton, Charles Olson, and Kenneth Patchen, as well as many portraits of Williams and Meyer.
  A group of views in the series shows of the birthplace of Thelonius Monk, while another group of still lifes represents books published by the Jargon Society and Divers Press.
  - BW001-BW379, circa 1951-circa 1988 (Box 61)
- Copy Photographs, circa 1978-circa 1993; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series V is organized into two subseries: Color Slides and Copy Negatives.
  This series consists of copy photographs of images created by Williams. They consist primarily of 35-millimeter slides, as well as a few color negatives on film 4 x 5 inches.
  - Color Slides
    This subseries chiefly consists of images related to outsider art.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by artist followed by unidentified outsider art, a gravesite image, and unidentified portraits.
    - Bailey, Eldren M., circa 1987; 2 slides (Box 62)
    - Doyle, Sam, circa 1985; 6 slides (Box 62)
    - Finster, Howard, circa 1979-1985; 54 slides (Box 62)
    - Forrester, Laura Pope, circa 1982; 9 slides (Box 62)
    - Hill, Churchill Winston, circa 1984; 5 slides (Box 62)
    - Holley, Lonnie, circa 1988; 2 slides (Box 62)
    - Hooper, Annie, circa 1986; 1 slide (Box 62)
    - Jones, Clyde, circa 1986-circa 1993; 4 slides (Box 62)
    - Martin, Eddie Owens, circa 1979-1987; 83 slides (Box 62)
    - McKenzie, Carl, circa 1984; 1 slide (Box 62)
    - Moore, A Doyle, circa 1979; 1 slide (Box 62)
    - Owens, William, circa 1985; 1 slide (Box 62)
    - Thomas, Martha Nelson, circa 1978-circa 1980; 2 slides (Box 62)
    - Unidentified outsider art, undated; 4 slides (Box 62)
    - Gravesite of an infant, undated; 1 slide (Box 62)
    - Unidentified portraits, undated; 25 slides (Box 62)
  - Copy Negatives
    - Unidentified portraits, undated; 3 negatives (Box 62)
- Electronic Files, 2006; Series VI; 0.21; (1 box)
  Compact disk with files by Williams and Meyer that provide information about components of photographs created by Williams, including color transparencies of portraits, outsider art, and images used in A Palpable Elysium, as well as black and white negatives.
  - Image databases and portable document format files, 2006 October 12-13; 169 megabytes (8 files) (Box 63)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services.